<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-11T21:46:39+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">reverx99</title><subtitle>Birkaç satır anlatı.
</subtitle><author><name>reverx99</name></author><entry><title type="html">Google ve Arama Kalitesinin Sessiz Çöküşü: Bir Araştırmacının Notları</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/google-ve-arama-kalitesinin-sessiz-cokusu-bir-arastirmacinin-notlari.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Google ve Arama Kalitesinin Sessiz Çöküşü: Bir Araştırmacının Notları" /><published>2025-08-11T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-08-11T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/google-ve-arama-kalitesinin-sessiz-cokusu-bir-arastirmacinin-notlari</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/google-ve-arama-kalitesinin-sessiz-cokusu-bir-arastirmacinin-notlari.html"><![CDATA[<p>2025’ten biraz uzaklaşıp, yaklaşık 10 yıl öncesine döndüğümüzde, Google’da yaptığımız aramalardan çok daha net, doğrudan ve amacımıza uygun sonuçlar alabiliyorduk. O dönemlerde arama motoru gerçekten bir “bilgi erişim aracı”ydı. Şimdi ise geldiğimiz noktada, bu deneyimin büyük ölçüde bozulduğunu görmek üzücü.</p>

<p>Bu değişimi irdelemeye kalksak; Ölü İnternet Teorisi, yapay zekâ tabanlı içerik üretim patlaması, reklam algoritmalarının agresifleşmesi ve SEO manipülasyonları üzerine uzun uzun konuşabiliriz. Ama sonuç basit: Arama sonuçlarının kalitesi dramatik biçimde düştü.</p>

<p>Özellikle benim gibi çoğunlukla Türkçe arama yapan biriyseniz, fark daha da belirgin. Yaklaşık 10 yıl önce “siber güvenlik” ile ilgili bir şey arattığımda karşıma kaliteli forumlar, teknik dökümanlar ve alanında gerçekten yetkin kişilerin blog yazıları çıkardı. Üstelik çoğu zaman bunlar, birebir sorun çözmenizi sağlayacak kadar detaylıydı.</p>

<p>Bugün aynı terimleri arattığımda, karşıma çıkan içeriklerin büyük kısmı 2025’in estetik trendleri ve SEO kalıplarıyla süslenmiş ama teknik derinlikten uzak sayfalar. Daha kötüsü, “sql injection nasıl yapılır” gibi temel bir pentest sorgusu bile artık sizi PortSwigger, Acunetix, Avast gibi kurumsal ve beyaz şapkalı platformlara yönlendiriyor. Tamam, bu kaynaklar faydalı olabilir, ama o eski underground forum kültürü, bireysel araştırmacı blogları ve özgün teknik paylaşımlar nereye kayboldu? Ne zaman “bilgi paylaşımı” yerini “pazarlama sayfalarına” bıraktı?</p>

<p>Bu durum sadece siber güvenlik alanına özgü değil. Yazılım geliştirme, donanım incelemeleri, hatta sistem yönetimi gibi konularda bile Google’ın algoritması son yıllarda kullanıcı deneyimini ciddi şekilde zedeledi. Arama sonuçlarında sponsorlu içerikler, affiliate link çöplükleri ve AI ile üretilmiş yüzeysel yazılar öne çıkıyor.</p>

<p>Evet, artık birçok kişi sorularını yapay zekâya soruyor ya da belirli konuları sosyal medya üzerinden araştırıyor. Ama bu, internetteki bilgi kalitesinin düşüşünü değiştirmiyor. Tam tersine, nitelikli teknik bilgi yavaş yavaş görünmez hâle geliyor.</p>

<p>İnternetin devasa bir çöplüğe dönüşmesi ve kaliteli içeriğin bu çöp yığınında kaybolması, sadece nostaljik bir kayıp değil; bilgiye erişim özgürlüğü açısından da ciddi bir problem. Bilgi hâlâ orada bir yerde duruyor olabilir, ama artık ona ulaşmak için eskiye kıyasla çok daha derin kazmak gerekiyor.</p>]]></content><author><name>reverx99</name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[2025’ten biraz uzaklaşıp, yaklaşık 10 yıl öncesine döndüğümüzde, Google’da yaptığımız aramalardan çok daha net, doğrudan ve amacımıza uygun sonuçlar alabiliyorduk. O dönemlerde arama motoru gerçekten bir “bilgi erişim aracı”ydı. Şimdi ise geldiğimiz noktada, bu deneyimin büyük ölçüde bozulduğunu görmek üzücü.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Silent Decline of Google’s Search Quality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/the-silent-decline-of-googles-search-quality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Silent Decline of Google’s Search Quality" /><published>2025-08-11T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-08-11T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/the-silent-decline-of-googles-search-quality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/the-silent-decline-of-googles-search-quality.html"><![CDATA[<p>If we take a step back from 2025 and return to roughly a decade ago, search results on Google were far more precise, direct, and aligned with what we were looking for. Back then, the search engine truly felt like a tool for accessing knowledge. Now, it’s disheartening to see how much that experience has deteriorated.</p>

<p>We could spend hours dissecting the reasons for this shift — the “Dead Internet Theory,” the explosion of AI-generated content, increasingly aggressive ad algorithms, and relentless SEO manipulation. But the conclusion is simple: the quality of search results has dropped dramatically.</p>

<p>For someone like me, who primarily searches in Turkish, the change is even more striking. Around ten years ago, a search for “cybersecurity” would lead me to high-quality forums, detailed technical documentation, and blogs run by genuinely skilled individuals in the field. More often than not, the content was detailed enough to directly solve the problem at hand.</p>

<p>Today, searching for the same terms mostly brings up pages dressed in the aesthetic trends and SEO patterns of 2025, yet stripped of any real technical depth. Worse still, a basic pentesting query like “how to do SQL injection” now leads almost exclusively to corporate, white-hat platforms such as PortSwigger, Acunetix, or Avast. These resources can be useful, yes, but where did the old underground forum culture, the independent researcher blogs, and the original technical write-ups disappear to? When did the spirit of “knowledge sharing” get replaced by marketing landing pages?</p>

<p>This isn’t an issue limited to cybersecurity. Software development, hardware reviews, even system administration — all of these areas have suffered as Google’s algorithm has shifted in recent years, eroding the user experience. Sponsored posts, affiliate-link farms, and shallow AI-written articles dominate the results.</p>

<p>Yes, many people now turn to AI for answers or use social media to research specific topics. But this doesn’t reverse the decline in online information quality — if anything, it makes truly valuable technical knowledge harder to find.</p>

<p>The internet becoming a vast landfill, with the good content buried under mountains of digital debris, is not just a nostalgic loss; it’s a serious problem for the freedom to access knowledge. The information might still be out there somewhere, but compared to the past, you now have to dig far deeper to reach it.</p>]]></content><author><name>reverx99</name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If we take a step back from 2025 and return to roughly a decade ago, search results on Google were far more precise, direct, and aligned with what we were looking for. Back then, the search engine truly felt like a tool for accessing knowledge. Now, it’s disheartening to see how much that experience has deteriorated.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sisyphus</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/sisyphus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sisyphus" /><published>2025-08-08T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-08-08T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/sisyphus</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/sisyphus.html"><![CDATA[<p>Sisyphus was trapped in an endless cycle. He knew he could never escape the struggle he was in, that this cycle could lead nowhere else. To win? To lose? These were merely things defined and predetermined by the rhythm of his own loop. Among the winds in which people lost themselves, his was a vast ocean.</p>]]></content><author><name>reverx99</name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sisyphus was trapped in an endless cycle. He knew he could never escape the struggle he was in, that this cycle could lead nowhere else. To win? To lose? These were merely things defined and predetermined by the rhythm of his own loop. Among the winds in which people lost themselves, his was a vast ocean.]]></summary></entry></feed>